


















    




<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        

        

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 17:22:54 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        
            <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
        

        
            <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/rss.xml" hreflang="en-us" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        

        
            

            <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/" hreflang="en-us" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
        
            

            <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/rss.xml" hreflang="en-us" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        

        

        

        
            <title>Absentia</title>
        

        

        
            
                <item>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    

                    

                    

                    

                    

                    
                    
                    

                    

                    
                        <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Osteoradionecrosis (ORN)</strong> is to a delayed radiation injury characterised by bone necrosis and failure of wound healing for at least 3-6 months, may result from radiotherapy alone or in combination with a mechanical insult.</p><p>The condition most often occurs after radiotherapy (iatrogenic) and might be referred to as post-radiotherapy osteonecrosis, ocurring on average 2-4 years after completing the therapy with an incidence of 3%.</p><p>Two complementary theories exist to describe the pathogenesis:</p><ul><li><p>Marx&rsquo;s theory describes a process of radiation-induced hypovascularity, hypoxia, and hypocellularity.</p></li><li><p>The fibroatrophic theory says that radiation damage induces fibroblast dysregulation leading to inability to repair tissue damage.</p></li></ul><p>Usually, large radiation doses are required for it to occur (30-60 Gy), the higher the dose, the more likely that ORN will occur.</p><p>Specific sites in which osteoradionecrosis is more commonly seen:</p><ul><li><strong>Mandible</strong>.</li><li>Chest wall - shoulder - humerus - scapula.</li><li>Spine.</li><li>Pelvis.</li></ul><p>Why bone specifically? As there is a more robust and redundant blood supply to mucocutaneous membranes than to bone and cartilage, the former tends to heal with time, while the latter may have a protracted or arrested healing course. Radiotherapy can additionally cause progressive obliterative endarteritis, as well as hindering the capillary regrowth of normal healing.</p><ul><li>Mandibular ORN;
Symptoms: persistent painful oral ulcer, odynophagia, pain-related trismus, occlusal changes (how the upper and lower sets of teeth fit when the mouth is closed), a foreign body sensation in the mouth, expectoration of bone chips, halitosis.</li></ul><p>Tooth extraction should occur at least two weeks before radiotherapy. Optimal dental health is necessary to lower the risk.</p><p>Treating diagnosed ORN requires surgical intervention, the bone must be debrided down to healthy, bleeding bone. Local flaps, regional or free flaps, and segmental mandibulectomy with vascularised bone flap reconstruction are some of the possible routes of management, hyperbaric oxygen therapy is also used to promote angiogenesis in hypoxic tissues, thus promoting optimal reparative conditions.</p><p><img src=https://gulavox.github.io/posts/images/Osteoradionecrosis/Clinical-photograph-of-exposed-bone-Notani-grade-2-osteoradionecrosis-in-the-left.jpg alt>
<em>Exposed mandibular bone 12 months after molar extraction</em></p><h1>Hello</h1><p><a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK430917/ rel=external>Source 1</a></p><p><a href=https://radiopaedia.org/articles/osteoradionecrosis rel=external>Source 2</a></p><p><a href=https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Clinical-photograph-of-exposed-bone-Notani-grade-2-osteoradionecrosis-in-the-left_fig2_331545389 rel=external>Image Source</a></p>]]></description>
                    

                    
                        <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-08-08:/posts/osteoradionecrosis/</guid>
                    

                    
                        <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/osteoradionecrosis/</link>
                    

                    
                        

                        

                        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/osteoradionecrosis/" hreflang="en-us" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
                    

                    

                    
                        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 17:22:54 UTC</pubDate>
                    

                    
                        <title>Osteoradionecrosis</title>
                    
                </item>
            
        
            
                <item>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    

                    

                    

                    

                    

                    
                    
                    

                    

                    
                        <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Cheilitis granulomatosa (CG)</strong>: rare granulomatous disorder, recurrent firm swelling of one or both lips. In isolation, it&rsquo;s called cheilitis granulomatosa of Miescher (CGM).</p><p><strong>Melkersson-Rosenthal syndrome (MRS)</strong>: classical triad of recurrent or persistent orofacial edema, plicated/fissured tongue (lingua plicata), and relapsing peripheral facial nerve paralysis.</p><ul><li>Orofacial granulomatosis: a syndrome grouping noninfectious and nonnecrotizing granulomatous involvement of the lips, oral cavity, and face, it includes CG and MRS, sarcoidosis, and Crohn&rsquo;s disease, although the latter 2 are sometimes excluded to make the classification specific to conditions with no systemic involvement.</li></ul><p>The complete triad is uncommon and may be observed in 25% to 33% of patients, even then the symptoms rarely appear simultaneously, and long intervals between the occurrence of paralysis and the first swelling have been reported. The disease evolves by flare-ups, yet permanent edema of the lips, and sometimes of the face, can be observed gradually developing.</p><p>Unknown etiology, commonly treated with corticosteroids.</p><p><img src=https://gulavox.github.io/posts/images/Cheilitis-Granulomatosa/Melkersson-Rosenthal-syndrome-presenting-with-A-facial-edema-and-tongue-fissuring-and.png alt></p><p><a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK470396/ rel=external>Source 1</a></p><p><a href=https://dermnetnz.org/topics/orofacial-granulomatosis rel=external>Source 2</a></p><p><a href=https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Melkersson-Rosenthal-syndrome-presenting-with-A-facial-edema-and-tongue-fissuring-and_fig1_367407730 rel=external>Image Source</a></p>]]></description>
                    

                    
                        <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-08-08:/posts/cheilitis-granulomatosa/</guid>
                    

                    
                        <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cheilitis-granulomatosa/</link>
                    

                    
                        

                        

                        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/cheilitis-granulomatosa/" hreflang="en-us" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
                    

                    

                    
                        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 16:45:20 UTC</pubDate>
                    

                    
                        <title>Cheilitis Granulomatosa</title>
                    
                </item>
            
        
            
                <item>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    

                    

                    

                    

                    

                    
                    
                    

                    

                    
                        <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Frey syndrome</strong> (Baillarger’s syndrome, auriculotemporal syndrome, Dupuy syndrome, gustatory hyperhidrosis) occurs due to aberrant reinnervation following injury to the auriculotemporal nerve, most often following parotidectomy.</p><p>Because nerve regeneration takes time, presentation generally occurs 6 to 18 months after surgery.</p><p>While not lethal, it can significantly reduce patients&rsquo; quality of life.</p><p>The published incidence of Frey syndrome after parotidectomy varies from 4% to 96%. The wide range of rates reported in the literature reflects great heterogeneity of symptom severity, reporting, and diagnosis.</p><p>The auriculotemporal nerve, a branch of the trigeminal nerve, consists of parasympathetics to the parotid gland and sympathetics to the sweat glands of the face and scalp. If injured, the aberrant regeneration of post-ganglionic parasympathetics (responsible for salivary secretion) along the pre-existing sympathetic pathways to the vessels and sweat glands of the skin leads to the development of Frey syndrome.</p><p>Facial warmth, flushing, and sweating in the territory of the auriculotemporal nerve overlying the parotid gland (preauricular skin, temporal skin, scalp, TMJ region).</p><p>Symptoms occur during meals, especially with spicy and sour foods.</p><p>Frey syndrome is less common in children and may occur during early infancy without a history of trauma or surgery. Symptoms usually occur around 5 months and can be misdiagnosed as food allergies since the Frey syndrome appears during the same period as food diversification. It can be distinguished from allergies: history of instrumented vaginal delivery, quick onset after a meal, occurrence with specific foods (sweet and sour) not related to common food allergens, rapid recovery without treatment, consistent and persistent location, absence of other atopic symptoms.</p><p>Approach is preventative, using fat flaps, musculoaponeurotic flaps, acellular dermal matrices, or other methods to provide a barrier between parotid innervation and sweat glands during parotid surgery. Botox has been used successfully in treatment but it requires regular re-administration due to diminishing effect.</p><p><img src=https://gulavox.github.io/posts/images/Freys-Syndrome/IMG_5391.PNG alt>
<em>Minor&rsquo;s starch iodine test: an iodine solution is applied and allowed to dry, starch powder is dusted upon the area, patient is given a sialogogue</em></p><p><img src=https://gulavox.github.io/posts/images/Freys-Syndrome/IMG_5392.PNG alt>
<em>Staining reveals areas of sweating, here the patient&rsquo;s extensive gustatory sweating has entirely washed off the starch powder with the iodine-stained sweat</em></p><p><a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK562247/ rel=external>Source</a></p><p><a href=https://medicine.uiowa.edu/iowaprotocols/freys-syndrome-starch-iodine-test-botulinum-toxin-treatment rel=external>Image Source</a></p>]]></description>
                    

                    
                        <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-08-08:/posts/freys-syndrome/</guid>
                    

                    
                        <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/freys-syndrome/</link>
                    

                    
                        

                        

                        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/freys-syndrome/" hreflang="en-us" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
                    

                    

                    
                        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 16:40:25 UTC</pubDate>
                    

                    
                        <title>Frey’s Syndrome</title>
                    
                </item>
            
        
    </channel>
</rss>
